Today's דף daf *daf* is פ"א pei alef. *Peh Aleph* 81, we're
a bit behind so let's get moving. Okay, the משנה Mishnah *Mishna*
dealt with a גט get *get* that was written
with
the wrong text where the consequences, the very consequential that the, all
these negative consequences particularly to the woman, תצא Teitzei מזה ומזה והוולד
ממזר *Teizeh mizeh uvalad mamzer*, etc. And then it moved on to
a, a more, from a more minor type of a mistake to
a bigger one, which was a difference in the husband's or wife's
names or in the locations, which said that even the rabbis would
agree that it would have all of these huge consequences, which leads
of course to a great הקפדה *Hakpada* in the writing of the
names of a גט get *get*. Okay, now it says, we pick
up in the middle of the, of the דף *daf* here. כל
אשר אמרו *Kol asher amru*, this is the case where has nothing
to do with writing a wrong גט get *get*, actually it's another
case where it seems that the woman is totally innocent, that there
was a case where there was no יבום yibum *yibbum* done because
one of the co-wives was an ערווה ervah, *erva*, was, was forbidden
to the brother-in-law, and the other one went and remarried, and then
it turned out that the first wife was not really married to
the brother, and then again all these negative consequences. So the גמרא
Gemara *Gemara* says, נישואין nissuin. זינו לא *Nisuin zinu lo*. It's only
a problem if that co-wife goes ahead and remarries, not if she
just has sex with somebody. לימא תהוי תיובתא דרב המנונא *Leima tehavei
tiyuvta d'Rav Hamnuna*, let's say this is a challenge on Rav Hamnuna,
דאמר רב המנונא Rav Hamnuna. שומרת יבם שזינתה *Damar Rav Hamnuna shomeres
yavam shezinta*, because Rav Hamnuna says a woman who is awaiting יבום
yibum *yibbum* or חליצה chalitza. *chalitzah*, what this woman retroactively we discovered
she was, because we found out that her co-wife wasn't really her
co-wife, so if she went ahead and she had sex with another
man, אסורה asura ליבמה *asura leyivma*, she's now forbidden to the brother-in-law,
you can no longer do יבום yibum, *yibbum*. And we are assuming
that we would only apply all of these negative consequences if she
did an act that would have made her forbidden to the brother,
you know, to the brother-in-law, right? If it was an act of
real consequence. But if she did an act that would not have
that consequence of making her forbidden to the brother, it wouldn't have
all of these ramifications. So the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* is saying, wait
a minute, according to Rav Hamnuna, even not being married to another
man, even just having sex with another man has, has the same
consequence. So why don't these have the same like severity? So why
don't these consequences apply? So the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* says, לא, נישואין
nissuin? והוא הדין לזינות *Lo, nisuin vehu hadin lezinus*, even though the
משנה Mishnah *Mishna* says they married another man, it would be true
even if they had sex with another man. והאי דנתני נישואין nissuin.
לישנא מעליא נקט *Vehai d'nasni nisuin lishna ma'alya nakat*, it's talking in
a clean language. It means, you know, getting married is a nice
way like when they sleep together. You don't mean sleep together, right?
You marry, it means you have sex, but that's a, but it's
even without getting married.
What? Right, all right, that's true. איכא דאמרי *Eika d'amri*, some say
נישואין והוא הדין לזינות *Nisuin vehu hadin lezinus*, that there was another
version that sounded like oh, marry, presumably that means also sex, right?
That would also have all these negative consequences. לימא מסייעא ליה לרב
המנונא *Leima mesayeya ley l'Rav Hamnuna*, let's say this supports Rav Hamnuna,
דאמר רב המנונא Rav Hamnuna שומרת יבם שזינתה אסורה ליבמה *Damar Rav
Hamnuna shomeres yavam shezinta asura leyivma*, that if she even if she
goes has sex with another man she's forbidden to the brother-in-law, and
therefore that's why all these negative consequences would apply even if she
just had sex. So the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* says, לא *Lo*, no,
wait a minute, נישואין דווקא davka *Nisuin davka*, no, no, no, the
משנה Mishnah *Mishna* should be read דווקא davka *davka*,
only if she married, okay? משום דמיחלפה באשת איש שהלך בעלה למדינת
הים *Mishum demichalfa b'eishes ish shehalach ba'alah l'medinat hayam*,
and because then that case of like hearing that the husband died
and remarried, you know, can easily be confused with the case of
hearing the husband died and then remarried and then the husband turns
up alive, etc. Meaning that's the paradigm case why all of these
things are אסור *asur*, right? It's sort of that case of you
heard the husband died, you remarried, and now actually particularly this case
where it's like it actually like was a death and there was
some consequence and she remarried, some event, it wasn't just it wasn't
a גט get, *get*. Anyway, so that's like the model case. And
that model case is primarily a one in which the woman remarries,
not in the where the woman has sex, and therefore we're really
only going to apply it in that case and we're not going
to apply it in the case where she just had sex with
another man. Okay, moving on.
הכונס את יבמתו *Hakoness es yevamto*, the other case is also one
where she was innocent, where this guy actually did יבום yibum *yibbum*
with one of the wives and so the other wife felt she
was free and she went off and then married somebody else, and
then it turned out that the wife that the man did יבום
yibum *yibbum* with wasn't his brother's wife because she was an אילונית
*aylonit* or whatever. וצריכא *Utzricha*, you need both cases. הכא קמייתא *Hacha
kamoita*, if you just had the first case about the case of
the, of her co-wife was an ערווה *erva*, משום דלא איקיים מצוות
יבום *mishum d'lo ikayeim mitzvas yibbum*, there I would say that okay,
you know, she's maybe we shouldn't have all these negative consequences because
no act of יבום *yibbum* or חליצה chalitza. *chalitzah* was ever done.
Everybody just walked away. So maybe there it's like, you know, there's
a little more responsibility in checking out that you're doing the right
thing because like, you know, if like nobody did יבום *yibbum*, we're
all just going to walk away, like before you just walk away
from the situation you check it out a little bit more.
I mean, check it out, how'd you check it out she's...
I don't know. I, you know, maybe you should have waited. I
have a very hard time understanding this. אבל הכא דקיים מצות יבום,
but when an act of יבום was actually done, like what are
people supposed to think? We did everything right. He did יבום with
my co-wife. Whoa. Like, we're done, right? So in that case maybe
we should like everybody should like be free from possible from negative
consequences. So אבל הכא דקיים מצות יבום אימא לא, Aval hacha dikayim
mitzvat yibum eima lo, so maybe we wouldn't have these negative consequences.
וישמיננו הכא, V'ashminanu hacha, if it just says the case of יבום,
משום דקרמיא קמיה, mishum d'karmya kamei, maybe it's the opposite. Here you
knew that one of you had to have יבום or חליצה. And
therefore maybe there was more of a sense that when you did
something wrong even if it was unaware and if it was in
hindsight and so on, you know, there's a sense of all these
negative consequences because you knew you started by being obligated in יבום
or חליצה. אבל התם, Aval hatam, but in the case where the
wife was an ערווה, the co-wife, דלא רמיא קמיה, d'lo ramya kamei,
that you started by assuming there's no obligation to begin with. אימא
לא, Eima lo, maybe you should not see the you know the
having married the wrong person you know in the same type of
sense of violation. I mean it was in hindsight and they didn't
know at the time and people wouldn't even assume there was an
obligation at all. צריכא, Tzricha, so you need to say both cases.
Again the problem is like yeah, so it still doesn't answer the
basic question which is like okay but bottom line is everybody is
innocent here and what it does seem very overboard. I really don't
can't answer that. Okay. כתב הסופר, Katav hasofer, now we're going to
get to the last part of the משנה Mishnah. which is easier
to understand, that the scribe wrote a receipt for the woman and
a גט get to the man and gave them the wrong documents
and then they exchanged the wrong documents. So obviously she isn't מגורשת,
megureshet, but comes along whoever this is רבי שמעון בן אלעזר Rabbi
Shimon ben Elazar who is it? Comes along רבי אלעזר Rabbi Elazar
and he says like no, no, no. That's only if you find
out the problem immediately. If after she married another man then you
say let me look at your גט get and you see it's
a receipt, you know you are not in a position, the first
husband, of making problems. Okay. Who knows what happened between then and
now? Okay. כתב סופר שובר לאיש וגט לאשה ונתן שובר לאשה וגט
לאיש רבי אלעזר אומר אם לאלתר, Katav sofer shover l'ish v'get l'ishah
v'natan shover l'ishah v'get l'ish Rabbi Elazar omer im l'alter, if you
just found it immediately, fine it's a problem. But after a while
it's not a problem. היכי דמי לאלתר והיכי דמי לאחר זמן? Heichi
dami l'alter v'heichi dami l'achar zman? What's immediately and what's after a
while? אמר רב יהודה אמר שמואל כל זמן שיושבין ועוסקין באותו עניין
זהו לאלתר. Amar Rav Yehuda Amar Shmuel kol zman sheyoshvin v'oskin b'oto
inyan zehu l'alter. If after the גט get was given and the
receipt was given and then they are there and they're still working
out details and sitting in the same room, you know they're in
the same sort of conversation and then you look at the documents,
that's right away. Okay. עמדו זהו לאחר זמן. Amdu zehu l'achar zman.
Once that meeting broke, any moment after that meeting broke, that's already
like anything after the meeting broke, you know we we we can't
assume we know what happened.
He essentially writes this הלכה halacha away. What? Essentially writes this הלכה
halacha away.
What do you mean? That's רבי אלעזר Rabbi Elazar לאלתר. l'alter.
I mean of course you're going to like be checking at the
time, you know that you got the right document. Really? Do you
think?
I don't know, because the way רבי, Rabbi, I mean maybe, but
but when רבי אלעזר Rabbi Elazar contrasts it to he doesn't have
the ability to make the second guy lose out. If anything I
would say that the simple sense of the, well you'll see the
contrast because the משנה Mishna, refers to a case where she's married
already to a second guy. So this says as soon as they
leave the room, it's you can no longer challenge it. ורב אדא
בר אהבה אמר לא נישאת זהו לאלתר. V'Rav Adda bar Ahava amar
lo niset zehu l'alter.
As long as she has not married a second guy, that's still
the same time. So it could be ten years later and as
long as you haven't married the second guy, then you can raise
problems. Okay. נישאת Niset once she married the second guy, זהו לאחר
זמן. zehu l'achar zman. Because that's he's picking up on the language
of the משנה Mishna? that you can't make the second guy lose
his rights, you know or whatever, you can't destroy a a new
marriage based on this claim. So the גמרא Gemara says תנן, Tnan,
let's take a look at the משנה. Mishnah. לא כל הימנו מן
הראשון לאבד זכותו של שני. Lo kol heimenoo min harishon l'aved zchuto
shel sheni. The first husband cannot say after a while, oh look
you know you only have a you have a receipt you don't
have a גט, get, there was obviously a problem, he can't do
that and make the second guy, I mean it's also her, but
you know destroy the second marriage as a result. So the גמרא
Gemara says בשלמא לרב אדא בר אהבה היינו דקתני שני. B'shlama l'Rav
Adda bar Ahava hainu d'katni sheni. There's a second guy because the
the problem is you know any that there's already a second marriage.
Anything less than a second marriage he actually would be able to
raise a challenge. But the גמרא Gemara. says אלא לשמואל מאי שני?
Ella l'Shmuel mai sheni? So according to שמואל Shmuel what does it
mean you can't make the second guy lose out? So the גמרא
Gemara. says שמואל Shmuel says זכות הראויה לשני. zchut harauya l'sheni. No,
no, no, it doesn't mean there has to be a second guy.
It means once she leaves the room, she has a right to
remarry. And once she has a right to remarry you cannot undo
that right. As long as they're in the same room, things things
aren't seen as final. But once that meeting broke and she leaves
the room she has a right and now you just because you
show some wrong document after the fact we don't know exactly what
happened between then and now. Okay. Very good. So now we continue
with a דף now we're back to where we should be, פא.
And this hopefully will go a little faster. Let's take a look.
כתב לגרש את אשתו. Katav l'garesh et ishto.
You wrote a גט get to divorce your wife. ונמלך, V'nimlach, and
then you changed your mind. Okay. בית שמאי אומרים פסלה מן הכהונה.
Beit Shammai omrim pasla min hakehuna. אוי געוואלד! Oy gevalt!
So because you went to a סופר sofer and said please write
a גט get for my wife, that created, you know oh did
you hear ראובן's Reuven divorcing his wife? What, did you hear ראובן's
Reuven divorcing his wife? He got the סופר, sofer, anyway, so people
then, the word gets out, okay, and therefore there's this that even
if in the end you didn't divorce your wife and then let's
say the guy dies, okay, people maybe think oh I thought I
heard she was a גרושה, gerusha, I think you hear that he
divorced her, and therefore because there there is a little bit of
that rumor impression or whatever that she might be a גרושה, gerusha,
he says we're going to have to not let her marry a
כהן. kohein. Now that's like terrible, it's like the opposite, right? And
we're going to get into the גמרא Gemara is there is like
לשון הרע lashon hara what you want to do or not לשון
הרע lashon hara but whatever. Anyway, if there's bad thing if people
are saying inaccurate things you want to correct it, not reinforce it,
but there's partly it has to do with a question about how
successful you think you can be, right? So once, once an impression
is created, Rabbi Weiss is fond of saying the only difference between
perception and reality is that it's easier to change reality. So once
the perception is created you might not be able to undo it.
And then what's going to happen? She's going to marry a כהן
kohein and people are going to say, a
כהן kohein married a גרושה?
gerusha? After the guy dies.
Because after the guy dies, after the guy dies, after the guy
dies.
And then you're coming back like oh oh yeah okay he he
was מגרש megareish her but then he sees they see her going
home and then they're like that.
Right, so that's obviously an obvious point. I mean it would make
a lot more sense if this was like the guy on his
deathbed, right? If it was 10 years later and they'd been living
together like how do people think she's a גרושה? gerusha? You're absolutely
right. So בית שמאי Beis Shammai are super super מחמיר, machmir, but
once there's this little whiff of her being a גרושה gerusha then
we don't want that to now become now she's going to marry
a כהן kohein after this after her husband dies and people are
going to think the kids are חללים chalalim or whatever. So we
have to just like go with that which and Michael of course
correct I mean my god all he did was he wrote something
and number two is the what if they're living together afterwards. So
בית הלל Beis Hillel says let's take a look what בית הלל
Beis Hillel says. בית הלל אומרים אף על פי שנתנו לה תנאי,
Beis Hillel omrim af al pi she-nasnu lah tnai, no the opposite,
even if he gave her a גט get. on a condition, he
gave her the גט, get okay but it was
conditional, ולא נעשה התנאי v'lo na'asa hatnai and the condition wasn't satisfied,
לא פסלה מן הכהונה. lo pasla min hakehuna.
So that you could say oh I mean oh my god everybody
thinks she's divorced they saw him give the גט get right? And
בית הלל Beis Hillel could be talking about the opposite extreme and
he died five minutes later so everybody assumes she's divorced right? No,
if she's not divorced she's not divorced you don't have to live
with a consequence of something that's not a reality. Okay now by
the way there actually is cases in the גמרא Gemara which are
interesting not discussed here of cases called ריח הגט rei'ach hagget which
is like I used the phrase before maybe consciously or unconsciously the
whiff, right? So if it has the whiff of a גט get
there are cases where we actually do say that she's פסולה מן
הכהונה pasula min hakehuna if it was a גט פסול get pasul
but it was close enough to being a גט. get Okay so
that's interesting right? Because בית הלל Beis Hillel seems to בית הלל's
Beis Hillel approach is no like if it ain't a גט get
it ain't a גט get? we're not going to make her suffer
the consequences. All right let's take a look at the גמרא. Gemara
שלח ליה Shelach lei
is it really דווקא this? Like let's say it's just a rumor
though people
well let's take we have a
problem right so let's take a look at the גמרא. Gemara Okay.
שלח ליה רב יוסף בריה דרב מנשיא מדבילא לשמואל. Shelach lei Rav
Yosef breih d'Rav Menashya mi-Dovila l'Shmuel. So the question was sent to
שמואל. Shmuel. ילמדנו רבנו Yelamdenu Rabbeinu let our master teach us. יצא
עליו קול איש פלוני כהן כתב גט לאשתו, Yatza alav kol ish
ploni kohein kasav get l'ishto, a rumor is in town that so-and-so
a כהן kohein wrote a גט get for his wife ויושבת תחתיו
ומשמשתו v'yosheves tachtav umeshamashto but they're still living together. מהו? Mahu? So
notice this wrote a גט get, for his wife and they're still
living together that's your case Michael. So people would say okay so
he didn't give it okay but that's not but if that's but
true people aren't necessarily giving there's not necessarily talk. They're talking because
obviously there's some question whether he did give it and then she's
still living with him which means that he would be a מחזיר
גרושתו machzir grushato right? Everybody understand? Not only is he now a
problem of a כהן kohein living with a גרושה, gerusha, it's also
a problem about anybody living with his wife well not actually because
if she didn't marry another man it wouldn't be a problem. Okay
anyway a כהן kohein
living with a גרושה. gerusha. He made his wife a גרושה gerusha
now he's living with her. Okay that's possibly what that rumor is
about.
מהו? Mahu? מה אי? Mah i? I'm sorry. So he said מהו?
Mahu? So שלח ליה shelach lei he sends him תצא teitzei, they
need to get
divorced והדבר צריך בדיקה v'hadavar tzarich bdika but we need to investigate
the the facts. Okay no it's interesting because in the past we
had
that's true in the past we also had תצא והדבר צריך תלמוד
teitzei v'hadavar tzarich talmud because when you have to analyze the הלכה
halacha I have to analyze then it's then you have to learn
it more. Here when you have to look at the facts you
have to inspect the facts, בדיקה bdika not
תלמוד. talmud. Anyway so מה אי? mah i? So what do you
have to inspect? אילימא Ileima
so anyway the גמרא Gemara, doesn't go that way and it sort
of takes the בדיקה bdika as maybe we have to decide what
the הלכה halacha is although I think it means we have to
decide what the facts is. Anyway what did that mean? אילימא דאם
מבתלינא קלא לא מבתלינא, Ileima d'im mivattlina kola lo mivattlina, if the
question is whether when there's a rumor do we basically try to
dispel the rumor or do we go with it? Again now why
would we like not try to dispel it? So רש"י Rashi says
again it just shows the power of perception. Here there is there
is a rumor that this woman whatever that this woman is divorced
and she's living with a כהן kohein and we're going to go
and say no no no no no we want everybody to know
it's a false rumor. So it could be we're very successful or
could be Everybody says, aha, you see that? He's got the בית
דין Beis Din in his pocket, right? He's living with this with
this divorcee and they're now coming ahead and they're coming to his
defense. Right? So if people really believe in the rumor, you're just
going to get yourself implicated if you try to change it. So
do we try to be מבטל mevatel the rumor or not? Or
do we go with the rumor and try to sort of follow
through on it, which is terrible, but maybe we have to do
that to satisfy people's perception?
Maybe before we actually do תצא, teitzei. we see if we can
מבטל mevatel the rumor first, right?
No, that's not the way the גמרא Gemara's is framing it. The
way the גמרא Gemara is framing it is what's our general approach?
Do we try to be מבטל mevatel the rumor, meaning there's a
הלכה halachic discussion or a policy discussion? When there are rumors like
this, do we try to be מבטל mevatel them or do we
think it'll just get us in trouble and we don't try to
do it?
But if we've already told her to get divorced...
well let's
take a... that's a good point. Okay. I don't know, so let's
see what the גמרא Gemara. says.
והא נהרדעא אתריה דשמואל הוא. ve-ha naharda-ah atrei di-shmuel hu. One minute,
but נהרדעא Naharda'a is שמואל's Shmuel's locale. That's where שמואל's Shmuel's you
know, area of influence. ובנהרדעא לא מבטלי קלא. u-ve-naharda-ah la mevatli kala.
And in נהרדעא Naharda'a they don't try to get rid of rumors.
So therefore what does he have to say to רב? Rav? Your
approach is you don't try to get rid of rumors. There is
a rumor, so people have this perception, you're going to have to
presumably reinforce it. It's such a deeply disturbing גמרא, Gemara, I have
to tell you, to reinforce you know this at the expense of
a woman getting divorced. Anyway but the גמרא's Gemara going to switch
gears pretty soon.
Okay. אלא. Ela. So here's the question. דאי קרו לניסויי כתיבה. de-i
karu li-nisuei ketiva. Now this works for the language of בדיקה bedika
better. When people say, the rumor is that he wrote a גט
get? for his wife. So the question is, well, what do people
mean when they say he wrote a גט? get Is that a
way of saying they gave a גט get to his wife? Okay?
And then there's a rumor that they're actually living in sin? Or
do we say even according to the rumor people are just gossiping,
but they're not saying he's living in sin because they just said
he wrote a גט, get they didn't say he gave a גט?
get. You got the question? Okay. So
וכי קרו לניסויי כתיבה. ve-chi karu li-nisuei ketiva. And even if they
were to say call you know say when they said they wrote
a גט get it could mean that he gave a גט get
to his wife. וכתיבה גופה מי לא קרו לה כתיבה? u-chetiva gufa
mi lo karu lah chetiva? But they wrote a גט get. could
also mean he wrote a גט. get Okay? So even if he
wrote a גט get. to his wife could mean he gave a
גט get to his wife and that could be what people are
saying. It could also be that people are just סתם stam gossiping
and they're not saying he gave a גט. get. אין. In. Yes.
דאי
נהי... de-i nehi... that wouldn't be a problem.
דמגליא מילתא דקרו לניסויי כתיבה, de-migalya milta de-karu li-nisuei ketiva, because if
some people do say to give a גט get they'll use the
phrase he wrote
a גט. get דילמא נתן קאמרי. dilma natan ka-amrei. Maybe what they're
saying is he gave, meaning, okay, so now if I got a
double, if I got a ספק ספיקא, safek sefeika, there's a rumor
that he wrote a גט get, which might mean that there's a
rumor that he gave a גט. get Got it? Okay. But once
there's that possibility that what people are talking about is that he
gave a גט get. and he's living in sin, so people might
be saying or saying something which might mean that he's living in
sin, תצא. teitzei? If that's what you're saying, that there's a really
like a ספק safek of a rumor. והא אמר רב אשי. ve-ha
amar Rav Ashi. I have another question. כל קלא דבתר נישואין לא
חיישינן ליה, kol kala de-vatar nisuin lo chishinan leh, which is like,
okay, thank God finally some end to this buying into a rumor.
He says if a couple's already married on the basis of a
rumor we don't go ahead and make them get divorced. Meaning like
if you take a look back at the בית שמאי Beis Shammai
of our משנה, Mishnah. right, בית שמאי Beis Shammai says it wasn't
exactly the same as a rumor, but it was a maybe it
was a perception, a whiff that the woman might be divorced means
what? We're not going to allow her to marry a כהן, Kohen,
right? But it doesn't mean that because there's these perceptions out there
or whatever we're going to make her get divorced. It might mean
we have some לכתחילה lechatchila policies, but not some policies after the
fact. All right and everybody see how that fits with בית שמאי
Beis Shammai in the משנה?
Mishnah Okay. So what...
so how could you say even if there was a rumor that
she got a גט get and that the כהן Kohen is now
living with his divorced wife? And even if that's what כתיבה ketiva
means, how could you say תצא? teitzei We don't do תצא teitzei.
on the basis of rumors, we just say don't get married on
the basis of rumors, we don't say תצא. teitzei So the גמרא
Gemara says, no. מאי תצא נמי תצא משני. mai teitzei nami teitzei
mi-sheni. No, no, no. What תצא means is if her first husband
dies the כהן Kohen who now people think is living with his
divorced wife, if he dies she can't marry another man. That's what
it means. It doesn't mean that she has to get divorced, which
did not sound like it at all. But I'm glad for the
conclusion. Okay.
Was there any mention of evidence to ask the person the people
themselves to testify?
Yeah, I don't know.
Maybe they're not doing that yet.
Yeah, exactly.
I don't know to be... yeah, you mean the... you mean the
כהן Kohen himself? Yeah I mean the... because no because the whole
idea of מבטלינן קלא mevatlinan kala means that... no no no because
the whole point of מבטלינן קלא mevatlinan kala means that even if
we know the facts and we know people are lying and they're
gossiping and they're saying the wrong thing, it still might be that
we can't do anything about it. We have to accept the realities
of perception. I know it's a disturbing גמרא. Gemara In some ways
it's a realistic גמרא, Gemara. like how... hard it is to change
perceptions. We know it's false, we know they're saying bad stuff, right?
But what we might wind up doing is because that's such a
strong perception is actually playing into it rather than working to dispel
it, right? Because it might be more counterproductive to work to dispel
it. It's a strange... I mean, it's a disturbing idea, but that's
the point.
It upholds the truth in a situation.
Yeah, like we have to just accept that like sometimes, you know,
you try to fight for the truth and the perceptions are so
much against that that you wind up
being smeared in the process. I know, it's very, very disturbing. What
can I tell you? So you're saying is even where if we're
going to play into the rumors, it's only going to be at
a limited degree, not to consequences if they're already married. So anyway,
the Gemara גמרא Gemara says one minute, im ken אם כן, im
ken, one minute, if you don't let her marry a second guy,
okay, there's still a negative consequence of what's already existed. Why? At
motzi la'az al banav shel rishon את מוציא לעז על בניו של
ראשון. at motzi la'az al banav shel rishon. The guy'll die, first
guy'll die, they'll say to the second guy, they'll say: No, no,
no, you can't marry a kohen כהן. kohen. Why not? Well, cause
there's a rumor that you already divorced ten years ago. So if
that, if once you're doing that, now we're dealing with again, what,
we're going to reinforce the rumors and have people live with the
consequences? So here the consequence is not that she has to get
divorced, but what's the consequence? People are going to say: You're living
with your husband, we're now saying that there was a rumor ten
years ago you were divorced. So any kids you had are now
chalalim חללים, chalalim, right? They're not kohanim כהנים. kohanim. So, ki hashta
motzi la'az al banav shel rishon כי השתא מוציא לעז על בניו
של ראשון. ki hashta motzi la'az al banav shel rishon. So the
Gemara גמרא Gemara. says: No, keivan d'mishani hu d'mafkinan lah כיון דמשני
הוא דמפקינן לה, keivan d'mishani hu d'mafkinan lah, it's only the second
guy we don't let her get married from, u'meirishon lo mafkinan lah
ומראשון לא מפקינן לה, u'meirishon lo mafkinan lah, people say they allowed
her to stay with her first husband. So she couldn't really have
been divorced. Okay. So therefore, must be that the whole problem is,
right, that the people will know that she wasn't really divorced because
she stayed with her first husband the whole time. So people will
just say, ati l'meimar אתי למימר, ati l'meimar, people, how will people
interpret the fact that she can't marry the second guy? Samuch l'misa
gershah סמוך למיתה גרשה, samuch l'misa gersha, no, it must be gersha
right before he died. Okay. So therefore, we can make this halacha
הלכה halacha for the second guy and we don't have to be
worried about the consequences. Now what's of course troublesome about this is
what you have just told me is based on how you the
rabbis are going to respond to the case is going to shape
perception, right? So because you actually are going... so if you can
shape perception, so then don't make... don't have any consequences, let her
get married to the second guy. People will say: Oh, if the
rabbis let her get married to the second guy, must be that
it was actually that she was never divorced in the first place,
right? So if the rabbis can shape perception, so now it sounds
like that the reason that we would buy into the kol קול
kol is because maybe we are concerned that the kol קול kol
might actually be true. But then it gets to your question: so
do a little investigation, you know? I'm... it's very frustrating. Not that
I don't understand what's being said, like in terms of what the
words mean, it's like it's hard to understand the policies behind this,
right? And here the Gemara גמרא Gemara acknowledges that based on how
the rabbis will act, that will shape perception.
The rumor was already in evidence, samuch l'misa gershah סמוך למיתה גרשה,
samuch l'misa gersha, that it was...
people will change their perceptions based on the fact that we let
her stay with the first guy and just didn't let her get
married to the second.
I mean, there was originally a rumor that was something different, and
the rabbis are now sort of buying into it and then sort
of changed the rumor? Right.
I know. But it's so strange. If what how the rabbis act
can change the perceptions, then, you know, do the right thing, guys.
All right, anyway, let's take a look. Amar Ami bar Chama amar
Rabbi Yochanan mishum Rabbi Yehuda berabi Ilai bo re'eh אמר אמי בר
חמא אמר רבי יוחנן משום רבי יהודה ברבי אילעאי בוא וראה. amar
Ami bar Chama amar Rabbi Yochanan mishum Rabbi Yehuda berabi Ilai bo
re'eh. So obviously that echoed, I mean, we didn't spell it out,
but that echoed Beit Shammai בית שמאי Beit Shammai that said just
because of a whisp of a get גט, get. we wouldn't let
her get married, but we don't rule like Beit Shammai בית שמאי.
Beit Shammai. Okay, every married to a kohen כהן. kohen. Okay. Amar
Ami bar Chama amar Rabbi Yochanan mishum Rabbi Yehuda berabi Ilai bo
re'eh shelo k'doros harishonim doros ha'achronim אמר אמי בר חמא אמר רבי
יוחנן משום רבי יהודה ברבי אילעאי בוא וראה שלא כדורות הראשונים דורות
האחרונים. amar Ami bar Chama amar Rabbi Yochanan mishum Rabbi Yehuda berabi
Ilai bo re'eh shelo k'doros harishonim doros ha'achronim. You know, the old...
you know, it's... we're not... the later generations don't live up to
the level of piety or purity of the earlier generations. This is
like a yeridat hadorot ירידת הדורות yeridat hadorot type of an idea.
Doros harishonim דורות הראשונים doros harishonim or it's just a general romanticism
of the past. Doros harishonim דורות הראשונים, doros harishonim, Beit Shammai בית
שמאי. Beit Shammai. Doros ha'achronim דורות האחרונים, doros ha'achronim, Rabbi Dosa רבי
דוסא. Rabbi Dosa. So what's the contrast? D'tanya דתניא, d'tanya, so Beit
Shammai בית שמאי Beit Shammai we know, a tiny whisp of a
get גט get, and already we're going to be so super careful,
can't marry a kohen כהן. kohen. Okay, it's seeing it as a
good thing. I know, it's a good thing that people, you know,
whatever, it's... real lives are... that's funny... well let's talk about that.
That's the real funny part about this. Doros ha'achronim דורות האחרונים, doros
ha'achronim, Rabbi Dosa רבי דוסא. Rabbi Dosa. What's Rabbi Dosa רבי דוסא?
Rabbi Dosa? D'tanya, shvuya ochelet b'trumah al pi Rabbi Dosa דתניא שבויה
אוכלת בתרומה על פי רבי דוסא. d'tanya shvuya ochelet b'trumah al pi
Rabbi Dosa. If a woman is taken captive and she's married to
a kohen כהן, kohen, you know, or she is, then she can
come back and she can go ahead and eat trumah תרומה trumah
and we don't say that she was raped and that she's asura
אסורה to her husband and she can't eat trumah תרומה. trumah. Amar
Rabbi Dosa אמר רבי דוסא, amar Rabbi Dosa, said Rabbi Dosa: v'chi
mah asah lah aravi zeh וכי מה עשה לה ערבי זה? v'chi
mah asah lah aravi zeh? What did this Arab do to her?
Like assuming that it was an Arab that took her captive. B'shvil
shemeichah bein dadeiha בשביל שמיכך בין דדיה? b'shvil shemeichah bein dadeiha? Because
he like, you know, fondled her breasts, tifsel m'unakehunah תפסל מכהונה? tifsel
m'unakehunah? Will she be invalidated from kehunah כהונה? kehunah? So we're not...
we're not going to assume even... it's funny, even though we assume
that she was completely at his mercy and that he might have
taken some sexual advantage of her, we're not going to assume that
he actually raped her. Now you could say how great that is,
Rabbi Dosa. is doing. רבי דוסא'ס *Rabbi Dosa's* letting her stay with
her husband, right? So the cost of being like extra פרום *frum*
religiously, you know, this extra level of purity, we don't even want
to wave a whiff of suspicion, there's real human lives that are
at cost. So it is true that there is a contrast between
דורות ראשונים *Doros Rishonim* and דורות אחרונים *Doros Achronim*, but the point
is, I think most of us, our, you know, we would side
with דורות אחרונים *Doros Achronim* here. And anyway, wasn't בית הלל Beit
Hillel *Beis Hillel* דורות ראשונים *Doros Rishonim* too? So בית הלל Beit
Hillel *Beis Hillel* also, you know, that's exactly, we would say that's
also the debate of בית הלל Beit Hillel *Beis Hillel* and בית
שמאי Beit Shammai *Beis Shammai*. בית הלל Beit Hillel *Beis Hillel* says,
you know, the human concerns have to be our, you know, our
focus, and בית שמאי Beis Shammai *Beis Shammai* says it's like that
old debate, I think it's just encapsulated in that, in the בראשית
רבה *Bereishis Rabbah* has a debate on בראשית ברא אלהים *Bereishis bara
Elokim*. בית שמאי אמר שמים נבראו תחלה ובית הלל אומרים ארץ נבראה
תחלה *Beis Shammai amar shamayim nivre'u techila u'Beis Hillel omrim aretz nivre'a
techila*. Like, where is our primary focus, you know, in terms of
our responsibility?
Anyway, the fact that, you know, that they're contrasting דורות ראשונים *Doros
Rishonim* and דורות אחרונים
*Doros Achronim*, I mean, I think that the point is, there's a
way to say it, which is that it's not like we think
we're doing anything wrong, we actually think we're doing the right thing.
But the point is, like, we can still have like this romanticism
about like, what are we losing in the process? You know, while
of course we're doing the right thing and focusing on the human
dimension, it's so like, but are we losing some sense of קדושה
*kedusha*? Are we losing some sense of טהרה *tahara*? So I sort
of see it in a more of a romantic way, but not
to say like we're doing the wrong thing, but like, you know,
to feel there's a sense of loss that comes with it. Okay.
ואמר רמי בר חמא אמר רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan משום רבי יהודה
בר רבי אלעאי בוא וראה שלא כדורות ראשונים דורות אחרונים *V'amar Rami
bar Chama amar Rabbi Yochanan mishum Rabbi Yehuda bar Rabbi Ilai: Bo
r'eh shelo kedoros rishonim doros achronim*. Come and see that it's not
like the earlier generations. דורות ראשונים מכניסים פירותיהם דרך טרקסמון כדי לחייבם
במעשר *Doros rishonim machnisim peiroteihem derech tarkesmon kedei lechayeivom b'maaser*. Now this
is a more obvious run of a contrast.
They would bring in their fruit through like the main gate in
order to be obligated in מעשר *maaser*. ודורות אחרונים מכניסים פירותיהם דרך
גגות דרך קרפיפות כדי לפטרם מן המעשר *V'doros achronim machnisim peiroteihem derech
gagos derech karpifos kedei lifatrum min hamaaser*. But in this generation, they
get them into the house through like the skylight and they're exempt
from מעשר *maaser* because מעשר'ס *maaser's* only, the grain is only חייב
*chayiv* in מעשר *maaser* when it comes into the house and when
it comes in the normal way. Okay. מן המעשר *Min hamaaser*. דאמר
רבי ינאי אין הטבל מתחייב במעשר עד eid. שיראה פני הבית *D'amar
Rabbi Yannai ein hatevel mischayev b'maaser ad sheyeira'e p'nei habayis*, the טבל
*tevel* is not obligated in מעשר *maaser* until it sees the inside
of the house and with that also means being brought in the
normal way. שנאמר בערתי הקדש מן הבית *Shene'emar bi'arti hakodesh min habayis*,
I've destroyed from the house. Okay. רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan אמר אפילו
חצר קובעת שנאמר ואכלו בשעריך ושבעו *Rabbi Yochanan amar afilu chatzer kova'at
shene'emar v'achlu b'sha'arecha v'savei'u*, even if it's just in the courtyard without
going into the house,
once it's in your gates. Okay. תוספות Tosafot *Tosfos* by the way
points out that even if it's not, even if you did not
have this ראיית פני הבית *re'iyat p'nei habayis*, you can only eat
from it עראי *arai*, you can only eat from it like, you
know, without a קביעת סעודה *kevi'at se'udah*, you can feed it to
your animals, you can snack on it, but you can't actually be
קובע סעודה *kovei'a se'udah*. Okay. Moving on. המגרש את אשתו ולן עמה
בפונדקי *Hamigaresh es ishto v'lan imah b'pundaki*, a man divorces his wife
and now...
He gave her the גט get.
*get*? He gave her the גט get *get*. And now afterwards they
spent the night in an inn together. Okay, maybe we don't know
whether they actually shared a room or not. Okay. Anyway, בית שמאי
אומרים אינה צריכה הימנו גט get שני *Beis Shammai omrim eina tzricha
heimenu get sheni*, she doesn't need another גט get *get*, we do
not assume that they had sex and that they were remarried through
an act of sex.
Or that they had sex but it was...
Well the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* will discuss those two possibilities. ובית הלל
אומרים צריכה הימנו גט get שני *U'Beis Hillel omrim tzricha heimenu get
sheni*, she needs another גט get *get*. אימתי *Eimasai*, when is this
true? בזמן שנתגרשה מן הנישואין *Bizman shenitgarsha min hanisu'in*,
that, here by the way בית הלל'ס *Beis Hillel's* more strict, notice.
Anyway, when is this true that we're concerned that they slept together?
Is if they had been married beforehand, נישואין *nisu'in*, they actually had
been living, you know, it wasn't just betrothal, they'd actually been married
and living together
before. ומודים בנתגרשה מן האירוסין שאינה צריכה הימנו גט שני U'modim be'niskarish
min ha'eirusin she'eina tzricha mimenu get sheini, *U'modei b'nitgarsha min ha'eirusin she'eina
tzricha heimenu get sheni*, but they agree that if they'd only been
betrothed and hadn't had sex
yet, that they do not need another גט get *get*, מפני שאין
לבו גס בה libo gas bah? *mipnei she'ein libo gas bah*, he
does not feel so comfortable with her that just after that divorce,
that, you know, they didn't have sex when they were married yet,
so how, why would we assume that now that they're divorced, that
that's what's going to happen. Well that's true too. But this also
does make it sound, as the גמרא'ס *Gemara's* going to say, that
the question is not that they had sex and we don't know
what it means, the question is whether they had sex or not
and that's why there's a difference between נישואין *nisu'in* and אירוסין erusin
*eirusin*.
So I'm just blown away with the permissiveness then of בית שמאי
*Beis Shammai* being so sure if there's a whiff of anything...
I don't know. I don't know. So anyway, by the way though,
there's another interesting thing that factors in here that the ירושלמי Yerushalmi?
*Yerushalmi* points out, I'll just tell you, it's a very well-known, if
you take a look very quickly, let's go to דף צ' *daf
tzadi* and look at the משנה Mishnah *Mishnah* there. Okay. This is
like the famous משנה Mishnah *Mishnah* that everybody wants to know why
is this the last משנה Mishnah *Mishnah* in גיטין *Gittin* and not
the first one. It says בית שמאי אומרים לא יגרש אדם את
אשתו אלא אם כן מצא בה ערות דבר *Beis Shammai omrim lo
yigaresh adam es ishto ela im kein matza bah ervas davar*. בית
שמאי *Beis Shammai* says you don't, a man shouldn't divorce his wife
unless she actually has been, there's some sexual transgression. שנאמר כי מצא
בה ערות דבר *Shene'emar ki matza bah ervas davar*. בית הלל Beit
Hillel אומרים אפילו הקדיח תבשילו *Beis Hillel omrim afilu hikdiach tavshilo*. Even
if she just burnt the stew. שנאמר כי מצא בה ערוה או
דבר *Shene'emar ki matza bah erva
o davar* and discuss how he proves it from that פסוק *pasuk*,
but okay, כי מצא בה ערוה או דבר *ki matza bah erva
o davar* or something. Anyway, so, so the ירושלמי *Yerushalmi* says that
that might be why they're debating this case. Do we assume after
a divorce that they might sleep together again? So according to בית
שמאי *Beis Shammai*... He's presuming that you only get divorced because there
was something real problem like adultery or some concern of adultery, so
we're not going to assume after a divorce that they would want
that he'd want to be or whatever they'd want to sleep together.
Why is he even with her then?
I don't know, they have to go, they're on a trip, they
go visiting their kids, I have no idea, but we're not assuming
they're sleeping together, having sex with one another I should say. And
בית הלל says no, maybe it was a small thing, and therefore
maybe they did sleep together again. Okay, is that ירושלמי? I think
so, yeah. Okay, so let's take a look at the גמרא. Gemara,
אמר רבה בר בר חנה אמר רבי יוחנן מחלוקת בשראוה שנבעלה. Amar
Rabbah bar bar Chana amar Rabbi Yochanan machloket beshero'uha shenivala. It's close
to what we said, and the גמרא Gemara is going to point
out that this does not work with the משנה. Mishnah He's saying
the debate is actually we know they had sex, witnesses saw them
have sex. The debate and the question is, what does the sex
mean? בית שמאי סברי אדם עושה בעילתו בעילת זנות. Beit Shammai savri
adam oseh beilato beilat zenut. בית שמאי says a person will have
sex with and you know and it won't be and it will
be not in the context of marriage, it'll just be fornication, and
we won't interpret it to be for the sake of marriage. ובית
הלל סברי veBeit Hillel savri and בית הלל says, no, אין אדם
עושה בעילתו בעילת זנות. ein adam oseh beilato beilat zenut. If we
know they had sex, we assume it was for an act of
marriage and that it was a remarriage. Now, what just to make
a thing points that's obvious but maybe it's not obvious is how
can something be obvious but maybe it's not obvious is, is that
is that does that mean that according to בית הלל anytime you
see you know two people out in the woods somewhere and you
caught them having sex that we assume that they're married because אין
אדם עושה בעילתו בעילת זנות? ein adam oseh beilato beilat zenut?
These people were married.
These people were married already. So look at רש"י. Rashi.
רש"י Rashi says
they were divorced
but they had been married, they had been married. Okay.
Anyway there's a רש"י Rashi somewhere that says
yeah look at the first
רש"י. Rashi. מה לי מן האירוסין הכא חזינן דבעל ואין אדם בועל
את אשתו זנות לבית הלל. Ma li min ha'erusin hacha chazinan deba'al
ve'ein adam bo'el et ishto zenut leBeit Hillel. So a woman that
was once his wife, right, and now they're sleeping together, it's going
to be in the context of marriage. But סתם stam you see
two people having sex, you don't assume it's for the act of
marriage.
Unless there was a rumor though.
Alright, yes, please. I hear what you're going Michael, let's not go
there.
Okay, so why should it be in the context of marriage? I
mean you know you could I mean imagine imagine you know you
were married to this this couple was married so they have some
see they have some effect. Right so they you know they just
happens they have Right,
just cause they were married doesn't mean they want to be married
again. Maybe they דווקא they got divorced because they don't want to
be married again.
Yeah, not not about this
I understand but there also is a reality but there also is
a reality
that people do get divorced and remarried and people you know when
they're because they've had the relationship they they can move back into
that relationship. But you're right. I mean בית הלל isn't saying This
is an interesting question as well you know is בית הלל saying
it's a ודאי, vaday, בית הלל saying it's a ספק safek you
know we have to be concerned about it.
And we can't ask them what they want cause it may be
like
Well then there's a question about like עדות edut and דברים שבלב
devarim shebelev and you know all those types of issues. Okay. But
all those are good questions. Let's look at the
גמרא. Gemara Okay. אבל לא ראוה שנבעלה, Aval lo ra'uha shenivala, if
we didn't see them have sex, דברי הכל אינה צריכה הימנו גט
שני. divrei hakol einah tzericha mimenu get sheini. Then nobody would be
concerned and nobody would require a גט. get We're not going to
presume sex and presume it was for the sake of נישואין. Okay
so let's see if that works in our משנה. mishnah. תנן. Tenan.
ומודים מן האירוסין שאינה צריכה הימנו גט שני שאין לבו גס בה.
Umodim min ha'erusin she'einah tzericha mimenu get sheini she'ein libo gas bah.
They agree that when it's from the אירוסין erusin she does not
need a גט get. because he doesn't feel overly comfortable with her.
ואם בשראוה שנבעלה, Ve'im beshero'uha shenivala, but the גמרא Gemara says one
minute, if we saw them have sex, מה לי מן האירוסין מה
לי מן הנישואין? ma li min ha'erusin ma li min hanissuin? Why
would I care if before it was betrothed or before it was
נישואין? And what does it have to do with לבו גס בה?
Right we know they had sex. The only question was what purpose
was it for. אלא מתניתין בשלא ראוה שנבעלה. Ella matnitin beshelo ra'uha
shenivala.
You're right. The משנה mishnah, has to be they didn't see them
have sex. The whole question in the משנה mishnah? is whether they
had sex. And that's why there's a difference between אירוסין eirusin, and
נישואין. רבי יוחנן דאמר כי האי תנא. Rabbi Yochanan de'amar ki hai
tanna. רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan
is going like a different version of this debate. דתניא אמר שמעון
בן אלעזר, Detanya amar Shimon ben Elazar, לא נחלקו בית שמאי ובית
הלל על שלא ראוה שנבעלה. lo nechelku Beit Shammai uBeit Hillel al
shelo ra'uha shenivala. Yes,
the משנה mishnah, is sounds like the debate is when we did
not see that they had sex. But he says no no no.
If you didn't see they have sex, everybody agrees she is not
married. We are not concerned with that. שאינה צריכה הימנו גט שני.
she'einah tzericha mimenu get sheini. You don't need a second גט. get
על מה נחלקו? Al mah nechelku? What was the debate? על שראוה
שנבעלה. Al shero'uha shenivala. They saw she had sex. In that case
בית שמאי אומרים אדם עושה בעילתו בעילת זנות Beit Shammai omrim adam
oseh beilato beilat zenut that a person even with his wife whatever
we're not going to assume that it's for the sake of marriage.
ובית הלל אומרים אין אדם עושה בעילתו בעילת זנות UBeit Hillel omrim
ein adam oseh beilato beilat zenut though for to with his wife
a woman who used to be his wife we're going to assume
he does not want this to be סתם stam an act of
fornication and it's done for the sake of marriage. So that's two
versions of the debate. מה Mah the גמרא Gemara says like this.
ומתניתין דאוקמינה בלא ראוה שנבעלה Umatnitin de'ukminah belo ra'uha shenivala according to
our משנה mishnah. they didn't see them have sex, במאי פליגי? bemai
peligi? What's the debate about? Cause according to that משנה mishnah. maybe
if they did see them have sex everybody would agree she would
be considered married. So what's the question if they didn't see her?
So the question is דאיכא עדי ייחוד וליכא עדי ביאה de'ika edei
yichud veleka edei bi'ah there were witnesses that they went into seclusion,
but they're not witnesses that they had sex. בית שמאי סברי לא
אמרינן הן הן עדי ייחוד הן הן עדי ביאה. Beis Shammai savri
lo amrinan hein hein edei yichud hein hein edei biah. בית שמאי
says we don't say that just that those people who are witnesses
to the seclusion are also witnesses to sex. We don't interpret seclusion
as sex. So all they saw was seclusion. בית הלל סברי, Beis
Hillel savri, no, אמרינן הן הן עדי ייחוד הן הן עדי ביאה.
amrinan hein hein edei yichud hein hein edei biah. The same people
that are witnesses to the seclusion, they are implicitly witnesses to the
act of sex. And therefore, since they're witnessing an act of sex,
if you fill in the gaps, so therefore,
therefore they saw that and that's presumed to be for the sake
of נשואין. nissuin. ומודים בנתגרשה מן האירוסין שאינה צריכה הימנו גט get.
שני, but they agree that if they were only in a room
together after אירוסין, eirusin, after a divorce after אירוסין, they don't need
a גט, get. דכיון דאין לבו גס בה, de'kivan de'ein libo gas
bah, since he doesn't feel so comfortable, לא אמרינן הן הן עדי
ייחוד הן הן עדי ביאה. lo amrinan hein hein edei yichud hein
hein edei biah. Then nobody presumes that we cannot presume they've had
sex. All right, ומי אמר רבי יוחנן הכי? u'mi amar Rabbi Yochanan
hachi? Did רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan really say this? והאמר רבי יוחנן
הלכה כסתם משנה. Ve'ha'amar Rabbi Yochanan halacha ke'stam mishnah. We rule like
a סתם משנה stam mishnah ואוקימנא למתניתין בשלא ראו שנבעלה. ve'ukimna le'masnisin
b'shelo ra'u shenivala.
So how can רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan say
that when they didn't have sex, everybody agrees it's not a problem,
right? רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan said
they're only debating when they had sex, he's going like the הברייתא'ס
baraita's version. But we have another statement that רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan
always goes by the משנה. mishnah. So right, every other, our משנה,
Mishna the version is that they're debating when they just went into,
when they just saw them go into a room together. The ברייתא
baraita says no no no, that's not a problem. The problem is
when they saw them have sex. And רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan goes
by the ברייתא. baraita. But don't we know that רבי יוחנן Rabbi
Yochanan always says we rule like the משנה?
We have a lot of different versions of different things.
Well, that's true. So the גמרא, Gemara, it's a, תרי אמוראי. trey
amoraei. So the גמרא Gemara says אמוראי נינהו ואליבא דרבי יוחנן. amoraei
ninu ve'aliba d'Rabbi Yochanan. And there are the debate of אמוראים. amoraim.
The אמורא amora that says that רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan is endorsing
the ברייתא baraita here does not buy into the idea that רבי
יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan. always goes by a סתם משנה. stam mishnah. Okay,
which is an interesting point, which the גמרא Gemara says elsewhere. Right,
if you say if you believe רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan always goes
by a סתם משנה, stam mishnah, that's going to limit, you know,
force us to strike off, strike out a number of statements of
רבי יוחנן. Rabbi Yochanan So the גמרא Gemara. almost always winds up
saying that when רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan is quoted saying something against
a משנה, that version who's quoting רבי יוחנן saying that does not
believe that רבי יוחנן says we always have to go like a
משנה. Okay, let's take a look now at the next משנה. So
that's a very important discussion of עדי ייחוד עדי ביאה, edei yichud
edei biah, which has other implications as well. I'll give you just
one other, a couple did not have a good קידושין, kiddushin, they're
married in secular law. Okay, maybe they didn't have a קידושין kiddushin
at all. Do we go by common law marriage? Do we feel
since they're living together and as, you know, as husband and wife
and everybody sees them, do we interpret that as if it's an
act of ביאה biah and an act of קידושין? kiddushin? Right? When
do we say עדי ייחוד עדי ביאה edei yichud edei biah and
things are interpreted as now they're married? What did they say? מחלוקת
הפוסקים, Machlokes haposkim, actually. Part of the question there also is if
it was a bad קידושין, kiddushin, maybe not because then we assume
it's all framed by the initial bad קידושין. kiddushin. If it was
no קידושין kiddushin maybe there's more of a reason to say, they're
trying to have a קידושין. kiddushin.
Yeah I know, but you don't think you need to. There's a
lot of interesting questions about that. Okay, let's take a look at
the משנה. המגרש את אשתו בגט קרח. Ha'megareish es ishto b'get kereiach.
If he divorces his wife with a bald גט. get, Now what's
a גט קרח? get kereiach? So basically they established for a כהן
kohen who is writing a גט for his wife, because כהנים kohanim
would sometimes divorce their wives a little bit impetuously and maybe or
maybe not, you know, or even regardless, the consequences would be much
greater because they couldn't remarry them after they divorced them. They wanted
to slow the כהנים kohanim down. So they made the act of
writing a גט for a כהן kohen a very like, you know,
intricate, laborious procedure. The way they would write it is they'd basically
have a piece of paper, and just say just my drawings abilities
right now, you'd have a piece of paper, you'd write a few
lines and then you would like fold it over. So now it'll
look like this. You'd have your, you know, you sort of dot
dot dot dot dot and fold it over. Okay. And then you'd
show the piece of paper, then you'd write a few more lines
and then you would fold it onto the blank. So the next
part would look like this, right? And the writing would be here,
you see, and it's like folded over and then you'd keep on
doing it. So by the end, and now each time that you
would fold it, you would tie it. So that by the end
of it what you would do is you would have a גט
that would sort of look, you know, like this, right? A lot
of bows?
Like that, right?
And each of these would be tied and the writing would be
on one side of each of these. And then what you would
do is on the outside of each of those things, you would
have signatures, you would have a signature. So a witness would sign
here, and a witness would sign here, right, and a witness would
sign like on the outside on the back side of the paper.
You're supposed to sign on every fold?
Yes, you do. That's what a גט קרח get kereiach is. A
גט קרח get kereiach is that they did not sign on all
the folds, that there's a fold left blank. Now the minimum the
rabbis required here is three folds and three signatures, as opposed to
a normal גט that only requires two. But if you went ahead
and made ten folds, you know, maybe they decided that that will
slow them down even
more, then you need signatures on each one of the folds. Okay.
Now רש״י Rashi explains, we'll pick we'll read we'll see the גמרא
Gemara says why they required that. Okay.
So let's say, so even if they sign at the very last
fold, which is like everything, so it's פסול pasul because they didn't
sign on the first ten or whatever it is, how many you
did. Right, yes.
That's what the משנה is going to say. So let's take a
look. גט קרח, Get kereach, so a man married her and she
was divorced from her first husband with a גט with a bald
spot, one of those folds had not been signed. תצא מזה ומזה
וכל הדרכים האלו בה Teitzei mizeh umizeh vechol hadrachim ha'elu bah back
to back. All the negative consequences. Okay. So she's really, she really
is מגורשת megureshet but the rabbis treat her as not מגורשת megureshet
so it has all those negative consequences.
How would anyone even find out? You'd have to undo all the
seams.
No, no, no, because the signature is
visible. Right?
Oh, it's like an accordion.
Yeah, it's like an accordion. Exactly. Here, give me that piece of
paper.
No, I got it. Alright, yeah, but it's good to show.
I might as well do it. Write, write, write, and then you
fold. Now this part is written, this part is
blank. Okay, write, write, write, no, no, right,
okay, and then you sign here, and then you do some more
writing, and then you do it like that, right, exactly, like an
accordion, right, and then you make a knot and then you know,
you sign here. So each section is signed.
So what's blankness? One without a signature.
Is that one of these folds doesn't have a signature? Okay. Alright.
Okay. Now גט קרח הכל משלימין עליו דברי רבי יוחנן. Get kereach
hakol mashlimin alav divrei Rabbi Yochanan. Now if you have
three, two or three, we'll see in the גמרא, Gemara. let's say
three כשר kosher signatures, which was the minimum, and you just have
a blank spot because you did ten folds, then בן ננס Ben
Nanas says fine, you can get פסול עדים pasul edim to sign
the other folds. Okay.
So it's very funny, right? The other folds you can get פסול
עדים pasul edim to fill in and nevertheless, right, and maybe it's
only one is one blank, we'll see if it's more than one
blank later, and nevertheless, if it's not so, then it's treated as
a פסול גט, pasul get, right?
Wait, isn't this the section you can't see, in other words it's
sealed
that way?
What? They sign... Oh, you mean... well, you mean... so that's an
interesting question that רש״י Rashi and תוספות Tosafot. discuss, which is when
you're filling it in with these פסול עדים, pasul edim, were they
there at the event or did they only come later? But so
they might have, but even if they were there at the event,
they can't testify, they're פסול עדים. pasul edim. So the point is
that this is really just to satisfy some rabbinic requirement that all
the folds be signed. They're not doing an act of עדות, eidus,
they're פסול עדים. pasul edim. They might have even come later, that's
debated by רש״י Rashi and תוספות. Tosafot, Okay. And nevertheless, even though
they're not doing an act of עדות, eidus, right, if it's not
done it's a פסול גט pasul get and all these negative consequences.
This is only after the first kosher signature, right? Because these are
the first one...
well, the גמרא Gemara will discuss, the גמרא Gemara will discuss. You
need, let's say, we'll see all that in the גמרא. Gemara Right,
obviously you need a minimum amount of
כשר kosher signatures. רבי עקיבא אומר אין משלימין עליו אלא קרובים הראויים
להעיד במקום אחר. Rabbi Akiva omer ein mashlimin alav ela kerovim hara'uyim
leha'id bemakom acher. No, no, no, the only people that can sign
are people that could be כשר kosher witnesses elsewhere. They could be
relatives because a relative could be כשר kosher in another situation if
he wasn't related to the people that, you know, to the husband
or the wife. Right. But if somebody is פסול pasul in other
situations, like they're a slave or they're a גנב, ganav, okay, a
גזלן, gazlan, right, then they could not fill in the
blank. Okay. ואיזהו גט קרח כל שקשריו מרובים מעדיו. Ve'eizehu get kereach
kol shekesharav merubim me'adav. What's a גט קרח? get kereach? If there
are more folds than there are signatures. Alright, now the first big
question is, why is it a problem? If you have three כשר
kosher signatures and you can even fill the blanks with bad signatures,
why is it a problem? So מאי טעמא דגט קרח? Mai ta'ama
deget kereach? What's the reason? So the גמרא Gemara says, גזירה משום
כולכם. gezeira mishum kulchem.
We're afraid that if you make ten folds, right, then the reason
you make, if you made ten folds that shows that you had
ten witnesses ready to sign. And therefore, if you have fewer than
ten witnesses signed, we're afraid that that will lead to כשר-ing kosher
the גט which said everybody sign, and you didn't have everybody sign.
Now, of course, if we really believed you might have said everyone
sign, then the other witnesses would have to be כשר kosher ones,
right? Because... yeah, so clearly that we allow there to be a
פסול pasul signature means we're not really concerned that this case you
said everyone sign. We're just afraid that it looks like you did
or it will be perceived that you did, so we can't leave
any blank spaces. So again, it's pretty amazing. Because of this very
secondary concern, the גט is still treated as so פסול pasul with
all these negative consequences, again we'll assume that this is according to
רבי מאיר. Rabbi Meir.
Understand, even if you had ten signatures on the first fold, right?
Still...
No, no, no, you only have one signature per fold.
But let's say you had
ten signatures...
I don't know, but there's a... yeah, but there's a... that's a
good
question. I don't know what the הלכה halacha would be. Okay, so
let's take a look. Let me just read some תוספות, Tosafot one
minute.
Yeah, so תוספות Tosafot doesn't like that. תוספות Tosafot says, yeah,
תוספות is a little bit bothered that if there really was a
concern about כולכם, kulchem, why are we allowing פסול pasul witnesses to
sign? Okay, he doesn't really. Okay, let's take a look. Let's take
a look now at the גמרא. גט שחרך כל משלימו עליו, Get
she-harech kol mashlimu alav, you're going to get פסול pasul witnesses to
fill in the blank. ורבי עקיבא, V'Rabbi Akiva, עבד מה טעמיה לא?
eved mah ta'ameh lo? Why does רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva not allow
a slave to sign? דאתו למימר כשר לעדות, Dasu l'meimar kasher l'eidus,
so people will say you had a slave sign on this, clearly
slaves are כשר לעדות kasher l'eidus because you know he put a
signature on his
גט. קרוב נמי אתו למימר כשר לעדות, Karov nami asu l'meimar kasher
l'eidus, so why does he allow a relative to sign? People will
say oh a relative signed, we see that relatives can be עדים.
edim. So the גמרא says אלא עבד היינו טעמא דדילמא אתו לאסוקיה
ליוחסין. ela eved hainu ta'ama de-dilma asu l'assukei l'yuchsin.
Now here's why we don't let an עבד eved sign. People know
עבדים avadim can't sign but they'll say oh did you see the
עבד eved sign? How did that happen? I thought עבדים avadim can't
sign? It must be he was freed. It must be he's no
longer an עבד. eved. So then they'll marry a free woman. So
that's going to be a problem, right? He'll marry a free woman.
So that's
true, גזלן דבר יוחסין הוא דלשתכשר. gazlan de-bar yuchsin hu di-lishtaksher. So
why don't we let a גזלן gazlan sign? Bar גזלן's gazlan's allowed
to get married, right? If the whole problem is that people are
going to assume that the עבד eved was freed, why don't we
allow a גזלן gazlan sign? אמר רב מתנא רבי עקיבא אומר אין
משלימים עליו אלא קרובים הראויים להעיד במקום אחר. Amar Rav Matna Rabbi
Akiva omer ein mashlimim alav ela krovim ha-rauyim l'haid bi-makom acher. It
can only be a relative who could testify in all other situations.
קרוב karov yes, גזלן gazlan no, not a גזלן. gazlan. אלא אמר
לך עבד היינו טעמא דאתו למימר שחרורי שחרריה, Ela amar lach eved
hainu ta'ama dasu l'meimar shichrurei shachreih,
because if they see an עבד eved sign they'll say it couldn't
be he signed and he was an עבד, eved, must be he
was freed. So what will they say if they see a גזלן
gazlan sign? It couldn't be he signed if he was a גזלן,
gazlan, it must be he did תשובה. teshuva. גזלן נמי אתו למימר
תשובה עבד. Gazlan nami asu l'meimar teshuva avad. And why is that
a problem? Because they'll think he did תשובה teshuva and they'll trust
him and they'll have him sign other things. So קרוב מאי איכא
למימר? karov mai ika l'meimar? So what are people going to say?
Oh relative signs, it must be what? He's not his brother? So
קרוב כולי עלמא ידעי דקרוב הוא. karov kulei alma yadei de-karov hu.
Fine, so that's רבי עקיבא. Rabbi Akiva. In principle you could have
פסולים psulim sign, but it confuses people and it sends mixed messages.
קרוב karov doesn't send mixed messages. Okay, אמר רב זירא אמר רבה
בר שילת אמר רב המנונא סבא אמר רב אדא בר אהבה. Amar
Rav Zeira amar Rabbah bar Shilas amar Rav Hamnuna Sava amar Rav
Adda bar Ahava. Okay, גט שחרך שבעה ועידיו ששה, get she-harech shiv'ah
ve-eideh shishah, if you had seven folds and six witnesses. ששה ועידיו
חמשה, חמשה ועידיו ארבעה, ארבעה ועידיו שלשה. shishah ve-eideh chamishah, chamishah ve-eideh
arba'ah, arba'ah ve-eideh sheloshah. עד כאן מחלוקת בן ננס ורבי עקיבא. Ad
kan machlokes Ben Nanas ve-Rabbi Akiva. The question if you can have
what type of פסולים psulim can sign is until you have a
gap of one. No no,
yes but that's not the point, we're going to get back to
that too. Right now there's only one bald spot, but in addition
to only being one bald spot you have three כשר kasher signatures,
right? And the minimum of a גט שחרך get she-harech that the
rabbis demanded were three folds and three signatures. So if you have
the minimum that was demanded by the rabbis, three כשר kasher signatures,
then we can debate what you can fill in with the fourth,
okay? With the other, with the
blanks. Okay? אבל שחרך שלשה ועידיו שנים, Aval she-harech sheloshah ve-eideh shenayim,
but if you had three folds and two witnesses, so you didn't
even have the minimum that the rabbis demanded, דברי הכל אין משלימים
עליו אלא קרוב. divrei hakol ein mashlimim alav ela karov. You could
only have a relative sign. Now of course you and I should
jump up and say what? If you need the first three, if
it's the basic three, you should need to get a כשר kasher
witness to sign, right? Okay, so that's what the גמרא is going
to say. אמר ליה רב זירא לרבה בר שילת. Amar lei Rav
Zeira le-Rabbah bar Shilas. So רב זירא Rav Zeira said to רבה
בר שילת, Rabbah bar Shilas, and notice רב זירא Rav Zeira taught
this teaching in the name of רבה בר שילת. Rabbah bar Shilas.
So he went to the rabbi who taught him this teaching and
he said back to him, he said מכדי כל שלשה במקושר כשנים
בפשוט דמי. michdi kol sheloshah bi-mekushar k'shenayim bi-pashut dami.
Three witnesses on a folded גט is like a normal two witnesses
on a simple גט. So on a flat
גט. So מה התם קרוב לא אף הכא נמי קרוב לא. mah
hasam karov lo af hacha nami karov lo. If it's the three
basic
signatures, how can you allow a relative? We need three as the
minimum. So אמר ליה אף לדידי קשיא לי ושאילתיה לרב המנונא. amar
lei af l'didi kashya li v'she-iltih l'Rav Hamnuna. You know what? I
also had that problem.
Now if you looked at the way it was said, it was
רב זירא Rav Zeira said in the name of רבה בר שילת
Rabbah bar Shilas who said it in the name of רב המנונא.
So he said you know what? I asked the person who taught
me this הלכה halacha that question. ורב המנונא לרב אדא בר אהבה.
V'Rav Hamnuna le-Rav Adda bar Ahava. Now רב המנונא said it in
the name of רב אדא בר אהבה Rav Adda bar Ahava and
he also didn't know. So he asked his teacher. ורב המנונא לרב
אדא בר אהבה ואמר ליה, V'Rav Hamnuna le-Rav Adda bar Ahava ve-amar
lei, and רב אדא Rav Adda bar said you know what? הניחא
שלשה במקושר דלאו דאורייתא. Hanicha sheloshah bi-mekushar delav de-oraisa.
Which is like okay, you know what, we could have figured that
out too. Yes, it's true the rabbis required three, but biblically you
only require two. But still, if the rabbis required three and they
defined this as the signatures of the גט, how did they allow
somebody who's a relative to sign? תניא נמי הכי, Tanya nami hachi,
we taught similarly, let's just read this fine. גט שחרך שבעה ועידיו
ששה, ששה ועידיו חמשה, חמשה ועידיו ארבעה, ארבעה ועידיו שלשה. Get she-harech
shiv'ah ve-eideh shishah, shishah ve-eideh chamishah, chamishah ve-eideh arba'ah, arba'ah ve-eideh sheloshah.
עד כאן מחלוקת בן ננס ורבי עקיבא. Ad kan machlokes Ben Nanas
ve-Rabbi Akiva. השלים עליו עבד. Hishlim alav eved. This is the debate
of if it's anything where you have three full signatures, if it's
a slave, בן ננס אומר כשר, Ben Nanas omer kasher, that's okay,
at least בדיעבד. be-di'avad. רבי עקיבא אומר הולד ממזר. Rabbi Akiva omer
ha-vlad mamzer. Again, we're back to the ולד ממזר. vlad mamzer. Again,
that's their debate. אבל כששחרך שלשה ועידיו שנים, Aval she-shachrech sheloshah ve-eideh
shenayim, three folds and two witnesses, דברי הכל אין משלימים עליו אלא
קרוב. divrei hakol ein mashlimim alav ela karov. Then everybody agrees you
can't have an עבד eved or גזלן, gazlan, the most you can
get away with is a relative. But again, we're allowing a relative
for one of the three. So now let's just read about the
response to this.
Because they might be favoritism? You were questioning whether we can use
a relative or not.
No, no, we can. Yes. רב יוסף מתני כשר. Rav Yosef matni
kasher. רב יוסף Rav Yosef says no, no, no. You cannot say
for the basic three that one of them can be a relative.
One of them has to, when you're down to the basic three,
everybody agrees that the third signature has to be somebody who's כשר
לעד, kasher l'eid, okay, somebody who's a complete normal kosher עד. So
התניא קרוב, Hatanya karov, what do you mean? It says that for
the third one we can have a relative. אמר רב פפא תני
כשר. Amar Rav Pappa tani kasher. Don't bother me about that. Cross
out that line. It should say כשר. kasher. Okay? So bottom line
is the גמרא says for the basic three, okay, everybody agrees there
are higher standards, but the חידוש chiddush is that we're willing to
consider that one of those three could be a relative. But obviously
גמרא really is bothered by that rightfully so and in the end
is pushing to say no, no, no, for the basic three they
all have to be כשרים עדים. kasherim eidim. The debate is when
there are blank spots that are left beyond the three. And tomorrow
we'll look at this question about that Micah was asking about what
if it's more than one blank spot, other types of questions and
so on, so all of that will be finished tomorrow.